Register of the Sergeĭ Dmitrievich Sazonov Papers, 1914-1928
Hoover Institution Archives
Sergeĭ Dmitrievich Sazonov Papers,
1914-1928
65019
Sazonov, Sergeĭ Dmitrievich, 1861-1927.
4 manuscript boxes, 1 leather briefcase 1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Clippings, correspondence, and writings relating to Russian political and foreign affairs in 1909-1917, Russian involvement in World War I, and the career of Sergeĭ Dmitrievich Sazonov as Russian foreign minister
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1965.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Kolchak, Aleksandr Vasil'evich, 1873-1920; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Vremennoe rossiiskoe pravitel'stvo (Kolchak); Russia--Foreign relations--1894-1917; Russia--History--Nicholas II, 1894-1917; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921; Statesmen--Russia
Biographical Note
Sergeĭ Dmitreivich Sazonov
1861 July 29 (O.S.) Born, Riazan' Province, Russia
1883 Entered Russian diplomatic service
1904 Appointed counselor of Russian Embassy, London
1909 Appointed assistant foreign minister
1910 Appointed foreign minister of the Russian Empire
1916 Resigned from his post
1917 Appointed ambassador to London but unable to assume this post due to February revolution
1919 Appointed foreign minister of the governments of Admiral A. V. Kolchak and General A. I. Denikin
1927 Author, Vospominaniia and Fateful Years
1927 December 24 Died, Nice, France
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains the papers of Sergeĭ Dmitrievich Sazonov, foreign minister of the Russian Empire from 1910 to 1916. Sazonov's memoirs in the Russian holograph original and English, French and German translations, constitute the bulk of the collection. Two bound volumes of clippings are devoted to the memoirs (excerpts and reviews) and two are devoted to Sazonov himself (mainly obituaries). The remainder of the collection consists of correspondence, biographical materials, and an office file devoted to the issue of Russia's claim to Constantinople and the Straits during the First World War.
The Biographical file contains an appeal to Sazonov, Sazonov's address book, and clippings relating to Sazonov, mainly obituaries on his passing.
The Correspondence includes a "general file" of sympathetic letters upon Sazonov's departure from the post of foreign minister in 1916.
The Office file contains correspondence relating to the acquisition of Constantinople and the Straits during the First World War. This file is very similar to the Office file in the Nikolai Aleksandrovich Bazili collection and is very likely part and parcel of it, but since it has been used and cited by historians as part of the Sazonov collection, it is left here. Researchers should, however, be aware of closely related material in the Bazili papers.
The Speeches and writings are primarily Sazonov's memoirs, including the original Russian manuscript in bound notebooks and partial and complete translations into English, French, and German (never published as a book). Two volumes of clippings include reviews and excerpts published in the periodical press. The original Russian manuscript contains material not included in the published edition (such as the final chapter). The designations "draft one" and "draft two" in reference to variant drafts of translations have been applied by the processor exclusively for the purpose of differentiating between drafts and do not reflect any original designations by the author or translator(s), which are absent.
Writings by others consists of one writing: the World War I memoirs of Robert Wilton, entitled "Behind the Scenes in Russia." This typescript should not be confused with Wilton's published Russia's Agony (London: E. Arnold, 1918), the content of which is entirely different and relates specifically to the events of 1917.
Memorabilia consists of Sazonov's leather briefcase, embossed "Ministr inostrannykh diel."
These papers were acquired from Lascelle de Basily as part of her husband's, Nikolai Alexandrovich Bazili papers, but were distilled from that larger collection and organized into this separate collection.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into six series: Biographical file, Correspondence, Office file, Speeches and writings, Writings by others, and Memorabilia.
Collection Contents
- Biographical file, 1916-1928. (Box 1)
  Address book, appeal, and clippings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address book, undated. (Folder 1: 1)
    Also includes notes and drafts of writings
  - Appeal to Sazonov by Mayor of Moscow Chelnokov, 1917 January 19 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings, 1916-1928 (Box 1)
    - General, 1916-1924 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Obituaries and death notices, 1927-1928 (Folder 1: 4)
      (two bound volumes)
- Correspondence, 1915-1926. (Folder 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and chronologically therein
  - General, 1916 July. (Folder 1: 5)
    Letters of sympathy to Sazonov on his resignation, 1916 July
  - Andries, E., 1926 March 11 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1924-1925 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Gamm, A., 1926 April 20. (Folder 1: 8)
    See also Speeches and writings/Vospominaniia/Typescript/German
  - Golovin, Nikolai Nikolaevich, 1920 (Folder 1: 9)
    Includes letter from Sidney B. Fay to General Nikolai Nikolaevich Golovin, 1920, and answers from Sazonov to Fay's questions about Russian foreign policy in the summer of 1914
  - Guchkov, Aleksandr Ivanovich, 1919 September 13 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Keller, M., 1919 March 14 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Oudard, Serge, 1926 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Persiani, Ivan Alksandrovich, 1921 February 18 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Schilling, Maurice (Shilling, Mavrikii Fabianovich), 1923 March 4 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Shebunin, A. F., 1920 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Strashnenko, Vladimir Aristarkhovich, 1915 April 28 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Verlag für Kulturpolitik, 1926 April 1. (Folder 1: 17)
- Office file, 1914-1917. (Folder 1: 18)
  Correspondence of diplomatic, naval and military officials relating to Russia's interest in Constantinople and the Straits during World War I, arranged by subject. See also the Nikolai Aleksandrovich Bazili papers for related material
- Speeches and writings, 1924-1928. (Folder 1)
  Statement and memoirs, arranged chronologically
  - Sazonov's Statement, London Times, 1924 May 11. (Folder 1: 19)
    Clipping. Includes lengthier clipping from New York Times entitled "Sazonov Denies Russia Caused the World War," same date
  - Vospominaniia, 1927 (Folder 1)
    (also published in English as Fateful Years, 1909-1916, and in French as Les années fatales)
    - Holograph (in Russian) (Folder 1: 20-21)
    - Typescript (Box 1)
      - Russian (partial) (Folder 1: 22)
      - English (Fateful Years, 1909-1916) (Box 1)
        - Draft one (Folder 2: 1-2)
        - Draft two (Folder 2: 3-5)
        - Incomplete draft (Folder 2: 6)
      - French (Les années fatales) (Box 3)
        - Draft one (Folder 3: 1-2)
        - Draft two (Folder 3: 3-4)
      - German (untitled)., Includes correspondence with A. Gamm and Verlag für Kulturpolitik inserted in draft (Box 3)
        - Draft one (Folder 3: 5)
        - Draft two (Folder 3: 6)
        - Proofs (Folder 3: 7)
  - Clippings, 1927-1928. (Folder 4: 1)
    Includes excerpts, reviews, and mentions in press
- Writings by others, undated. (Folder 4: 2)
  Robert Wilton, "Behind the Scenes in Russia"
- Memorabilia, undated. (Folder Vault)
  Sazonov's leather briefcase, embossed "Ministr inostrannykh diel"